[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
e-r. s radio is brought to you by the it
computer society and by It software
Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software if slow QA processes bottleneck
you or your software engineering team
and you're releasing slower because of
it you need to check out QA wolf.com QA
wolf gets engineering teams to 80% Auto
ated end to-end test coverage and helps
them ship five times faster by reducing
QA Cycles from hours to minutes with
over fstar reviews on G2 and customer
testimonials from salesloft drada
AutoTrader and many more you're in good
hands go to QA wolf.com to see if they
can help you squash the QA
bottleneck welcome to software
engineering radio I'm your host joavan
aspon and today I'll be discussing
architecture modernization with Nick
tune and Jean George in Nick works with
product and Technology leaders to map
strategy model domains design
architecture and build continues
delivery teams he's the author of
principles and practices of domain
driven design and co-author with John
George perin of architecture
modernization Jean George is jgp for
short is the chief Innovation officer at
ABIA data the chair of the open data
contract standard is a co-founder of the
Ida user group and author of multiple
books including implementing data mesh
sparking action second edition and of
course architecture modernization with
Nick nickan George welcome to software
engineering radio is there anything I
miss that you would like to add well
thank you thank you for having us just
to show off a little bit I'm also a
lifetime IBM Champion I'm a PayPal
champion and recently I've been data
mesh MVP and MVP stands for most
valuable player not minimum valuable
product
here Nick anything add I think I came
like third in the 100 meters at primary
school at sports day
once you beat me so let's talk now about
the subject of this podcast so about
architecture modernization so let's
start with some context for our
listeners so my first question is what
is architecture modernization as you
propose it is it a set of activities is
a process is a methodology or something
else so the general concept is as we
build software system
they get older and the world around us
changes new technologies become
available new patterns and practices and
ways of doing architecture become
available our company's business model
changes and so we have a software system
that is quite behind what's possible in
the modern day so modernization is
really removing those disadvantages of
the old systems by using modern
practices Technologies and thinking I
would say so it's really a topic or a
theme I wouldn't say it's a process I
wouldn't say it's a technology I
wouldn't say it's a very specific thing
it's just the process or the act of
doing something in a general sense okay
so is it aimed at Large Scale changes or
incremental improvements because from
reading the book The Way It Is described
there is also the concept of creating a
a group of people that will supervise
these changes and will help the teams in
doing this so reading it seems to be a
large scale Endeavor and something that
is a kind of a big thing or is it more
incremental improvements in daytoday
work well I think it depends on the
context but I mean for a lot of
companies nobody wants to do
modernization nobody wants to spend
three five years fixing the Legacy
systems but at the same time Business
Leaders want to be able to build new
products to expand to new customer
segments and new countries when the
Legacy system doesn't allow you to do
that sometimes you have to do large
scale changes obviously we would all
prefer to do small day-to-day changes
and if you have good discipline and good
practices and you don't build up
technical debt yeah you can do this on a
more gradual ongoing basis and not need
to do big projects okay and it's also
kind of oneof activity or an ongoing one
or a bit of both you know what I mean is
does it have a kind of a start and an
ending and then you say now we have a
modern architecture or you know it's
something that you continuously do to
keep the architecture somehow
relevant I mean there might be periods
where we're doing more or less
modernization the more technical debt we
build up the more difficult our Legacy
systems become to work with the more we
have to invest in those so there might
be a period where the company's talking
about modernizing and then when the
system becomes less of a bottleneck less
of a blocker to the business kind of
starts to we stop talking about that so
there's not really an end date um not
really a start date either but there are
exceptions one of the case studies in
the book is Open Table they did a big
modernization around 2022 around that
time period they basically stopped all
product development work did this big
modernization project for 9 months and
then carried on again as normal so you
can do it that way but most of the time
it's more of a fuzzy thing with big
Peaks and then starts to taper out maybe
and there's always this ongoing
continuing to add product features
versus doing modernization work that's
usually a difficult topic that's always
a challenge especially when it comes to
okrs and road maps and everything yeah
because I guess everybody wants to have
a system with more features that serves
more customer needs and so spending time
on modernization seems to be kind of
maybe a cost more than something that
will enable future business I would
imagine at at least this is the
perception that some have yes it's an
investment yeah yes so this looks to me
that is kind of a bit of both one of
activity and ongoing one and this
depends very much on the current context
of of the system so some kind of periods
of big modernization efforts then work
as usual maybe the team trying to keep
the technical Dept at under control and
then again potentially another big
effort and so on and so forth yeah I
think he's a business question what does
your business want to achieve are you
looking to expand into new countries how
difficult how expensive would it be to
do that with your current systems it
might not be possible so that would be
the driver of the scope what are the
business goals and how does the current
system constrain those goals yeah okay
and another aspect you say that modern
software architecture is social
technical so involves both technological
and social aspects how does that affect
the architecture modernization choices
and decisions what I mean is how these
social and Technologic aspects work with
each other yeah so at the end of the day
we have to make decisions about which
team own which parts of the system and
that can actually have an impact on how
we design the system sometimes there are
different ways to slice your
architecture and the way to think about
that
is if we slice it up in one way and we
have had teams owning this bit and this
bit versus slicing it another way and
teams owning different bits what would
allow teams to work more independently
so that they're not blocked or having to
coordinate their work and we can also
think from a reliability perspective
which way of slicing the architecture
and the teams is likely to result in the
fewest bugs so that might involve doing
some Dem manger in design and looking at
what do we consider transactions to
which bits of data do we need to update
atomically that will shape our
architecture boundaries and our team
boundaries in terms of these two aspects
is there one that is more important than
the other like are social aspects more
or less important than the technology
one or they are at the same level what
would you say in your experience it's
hard to really say that one's more
important than the other I think both
need to be done really well I wouldn't
like to say either one's easy so no I
wouldn't pick either one I would say
both are difficult challenges and the
actual problem is how to do a joint
optimization to find a compromise that
spans across both the organization and
the
software okay if I may add to that a
little bit it also depends on where you
are in the project because the social
aspect to your project or to your
modernization where it's software or
data you may feel it differently at
different time of your project okay so
first at the very beginning it's a
business decision as Nick said and
you've got to go through acceptance of
that part so there's already a bit of
socio going on there and then as you
roll out your architecture methods are
changing and then when you use a magic
change word okay you've got to coach
people with this change and that's also
where the socio aspect is really
important yeah and in my experience I
think it's often undermined yeah and
talking about these things I'd like to
know if you from your experience so now
of course when we talk about social
aspects there is always conv law that
comes in play yeah so for our listeners
is basically convin law says that the
shape of the team structure follows the
shape of the system being built now
usually when we talk about con law we
talk from a system perspective say this
is the architect
now this is how the teams should be
structured to create to implement this
system according to this design have you
seen in some companies maybe you can
have some examples of doing the other
thing like this is a team structure we
have that we cannot change and so we
need to match the architecture to what
we've got in terms of structure have you
ever seen anything like that yeah so I
have worked in the UK government and
they were doing a digital transformation
and the digital bit was being built by
this new digital organization and they
had their own
CTO and the internal facing stuff owning
a lot of the Legacy systems and
databases that was owned by the
Enterprise it team who had their own
CTO and so when you're building a
digital service you're a digital usually
means customer facing UI website front
end when you're implementing and you
feature your data has to come from
somewhere when you want to store data
you have to store it somewhere and so a
feature runs all the way from UI from
front office to back office you got the
integration in between the databases I
talked about so yeah I was on this
project we had this problem I gave some
talks about this almost 10 years ago now
actually and we proposed to change the
architecture so that we didn't have this
dependency like this front and back on
the front we are all doing stuff inhouse
sitting together in an agile way the
backend bits they were Outsourcing lots
of it to different vendors using
different technology Stacks so very
difficult to collaborate when a feat
across this organizational boundary it
was very difficult to even help a lot of
coordination was needed so we proposed a
restructuring but that would have meant
one of these CTO would have to give
something to the other one and they were
both fighting to become the global
overall CTO so neither of them wanted to
obviously give away anything it was all
about power structure very dominated by
politics that's interesting this is
where the social aspects actually had
the really were the most important thing
in this case so they even if maybe a
system designed differently changing the
structure would they be more efficient
to use maybe easier to support still the
way that there was this structure there
that nobody wanted to change some bits
reflect
but some bits were not and the two
different departments were going in
completely different directions that
would make it harder to change different
Tex Stacks different ways of working it
was it wouldn't have been possible to
bring it together later on either how
did you manage to deliver this project
must have been really hard yeah it was
quite difficult there were situations
where we were building this new UI and
we wanted to change the user experience
like we had user researchers they were
going out every week talk to citizens of
the UK they were involving developers
they were presenting these videos of all
the user research sessions and we were
like oh it's amazing so many things we
can improve and make our citizens happy
and it would be like let's add a new bit
of data on this page let's add some more
data let's collect a bit of information
over here and then we started to hit
these blockers and it's like well we
have this Legacy database which sits in
a DMZ owned by a different vendor and
the XML schema is here and it passes
through these different different
systems so if you want to change a
schema you have to update it in four
places you need to pay a vendor like
tens of thousands of pounds just to give
you a quote for how much it will
fix so yeah you just can't improve the
product and I think people started to
call this lipstick on a pig you can do
these Digital Services but if you can't
actually change the business rules and
the data and make those deep
improvements you're just putting a new
website on an old Legacy system which
has some benefits but not as much as it
could be having yeah I think we'll talk
about maybe later also we talk a bit how
to go with implementing an architecture
modernization program because these kind
of problem seem to be potential
showstoppers now a question about the
architecture modernization approach you
propose yeah in the book now there are
other also books about improving Legacy
systems modernizing architectures in a
way what is different in what you
propose compared to what was already
there I don't really think there was
much there to be honest I don't really
think there's a lot of content out there
on this topic there are books that talk
about refactoring like Michael feathers
working with Legacy code but this book
really isn't about that on a tactical
implementation level it's more on what
are all of the dots you need to put
together to do modernization
successfully so I was writing blog posts
about this for a number of years the
different aspects thinking about how
this all fits together I didn't really
see that much out there and the book
does doesn't really talk about an
approach or a framework the book covers
the different topics you need to think
about to do modernization well from a
strategic level to an architecture level
to migration level but it doesn't say a
specific way of doing things it
recommends techniques like wly mapping
and event storming and DDD but you don't
have to use those there's no
certification you know it's not it's not
a step-by-step process it's more tools
and how you can fit them together and
yes the way I see it is also basically
doesn't stop simply what you need to do
at the code base it's more general what
you need to do at the system broadly
defined also what you've got around your
software system or the
organization how it works how it works
how people work together and skills and
everything else so it seems to be more
General than the typical things you read
about refactoring systems on improving
architecture yeah it's not a refactoring
book it's not many technical patterns in
there there is some stuff on DDD there
is some stuff around how you can migrate
from your old to your new architecture
typically you're going to be using some
form of the Strangler fig with an
incremental migration so you got your
new system and your old system running
in parallel and you're moving bits
across and you have to ask questions
like do we migrate the reads or the
writes first so we can take a bit out of
the Legacy maybe it's a part of your
website
and it's presenting some data but the
information still comes into your system
from the Legacy so you have to have some
synchronization between those two so
touches on those migration patterns
shows how you can do things like
software design event storming and what
that would look like in your code but
yeah it's not a detailed book about
refracturing patterns yeah okay now if
we go into a bit more detail so
basically as we said there is looks at
all aspects of the system and so as I
understand it this approach is about
potentially revisiting pretty much
everything around the old system you
know Technologies the design the
features the team structure the team
skills as opposed to doing the same
things but better somehow so it's kind
of revisiting things and having a better
look at what we are doing with our
system and see how we can have a better
one you know more modern in many
respects but now I have a question about
what kind of criteria we can use to
decide in our system if you want to
modernize it which aspects to revisit
and which aspects to keep the same yeah
so some of the aspects we might want to
revisit are the UI for example do we
just fix the code or do we make some UI
improvements as well like the government
example I talked about something else we
might ask is do we make some
improvements to The Domain model and the
data model the simplest or the lowest
version might be you just rebuild the
old system in a new tech but if your
code's tightly coupled and poorly
designed you're going to bring that into
the new version so you might also desire
to improve your domain model domain
model is how you represent business
Concepts in your code it's the language
you use as systems get older very often
the way people talk about the product
doesn't match the words used in the
software very generically we might talk
about things like a customer but in the
code we might use words like a client
that's a simple example but over time
get these mismatches so that's one of
the areas we can invest in a domain
model and for me the question is always
what's the business potential we need to
understand if we could completely
modernize the ux completely refactor our
code and make it a perfect domain model
what would that be worth how much would
it cost then we can do that on a Case by
case basis for different parts of our
system and work out what's the best Roi
for each area in some cases it might
just be lift and shift to the cloud and
in some cases it might be a complete
revamp from the code infrastructure ux
domain model what about you know team
structure team skills and all these kind
of aspects as well how do you decide
that does it come after you decide well
ideally the domain model and potentially
the architecture is this the ideal
situation yeah so as we're thinking
about the new architecture and what the
new boundaries will be we have to start
thinking how do we break up our business
and how might we structure our teams
around the architecture so those three
things are always the same equation okay
so you mentioned youi user experience
the model so of all these many aspects
are there some that are special in the
sense that you always want to revisit
them probably not no I don't think
anything is always um sometimes you
might keep your existing software and
you might just change the code you might
fix some of the most complex bits in
your legacy sometimes you might change
the tech and not much change in the
actual design of the software so I think
each of those bits is independently
changeable obviously it depends
sometimes you might have a legacy system
where the UI is very coupled to the code
and we can't change one without the
other or sometimes a legacy code might
be so difficult to work with that if we
want to change a it will be so expensive
we may as well fix it the main model as
well so the things can be changed
separately but we have to look at how
couple they are and how difficult it is
to change each part
independently okay have you got a kind
of real life example you know showing
how to apply some of this criteria you
know how to think about what we need to
revisit and how to proceed have we got
any real project example you can give us
of course you know without naming
names yeah so we could start with the UK
government that was 10 years ago so
probably not too many Secrets there
anymore in that example the government
system had existed for decades the
business rules had existed for someone
told me maybe even more than a 100 years
what was happening was when businesses
were submitting their property tax
assessments the government works out how
much tax you should pay and legally
you're allowed to dispute that and
complain so so everyone was taking their
legal rights and disputing how much tax
they pay government was getting a lot of
these cases building up they didn't have
enough support workers to process all
the
cases and so businesses were taking the
government to court the government
wasn't even turning up at court because
they didn't have enough people to be
there they were losing a lot of money
bad reputation doesn't look good so
obviously when we've got a crisis like
that it's very easy to make a case for
modernizing and modernizing properly I
think the other aspect of the government
was there was an initiative on a whole
government level to do some
modernization work and the government
set Global standards on what's
acceptable in terms of how the ux works
in terms of Technology practices so we
have the individual business areas that
have varying needs and then we might
have Global policies in our company that
dictate where we have constraints where
we must do things to a certain standard
for examp example in this case the
government was setting some expectations
as some standards at least for part of
the user experience and the systems oh
yeah they were setting a lot of
Standards you can see online um GDs
government digital service in the UK
they had a list of like 10 or 11 points
and if you were modernizing some systems
you had to go to an assessment at their
offices in London and if you didn't meet
all the criteria they would say you're
not mov to the next phase you're not
allowed to open your service to the
public okay if you couldn't demonstrate
for example that you were iterating with
real user feedback so we had all those
user research sessions and we were able
to show them that and they were you know
very happy with that we were using the
government design style kits we were
measuring our service how it was being
used we were using things like
continuous integration which are minimum
standards we were putting our code open
so we ticked a lot of these boxes that
were minimum requirements okay so in a
way in this case you didn't have to
think too hard to see what to revisit
because there were some precise
requirements in many respects in this
case yeah on a global level there were
some requirements about the minimum
level the minimum requirements in each
area and so that make a lot of decisions
for you we also were using this
government platform that allowed us to
spin up microservices new frontend
applications in a very conventional way
with a paved Road so again that already
gave us a lot of the foundations and
constraints we needed so we didn't have
to think a lot there either the
technology and the infrastructure those
things were taken care of and decided
for us and on another aspect so you
mentioned this before as well that in
the book you list a set of activities
tools things that can be used to think
about modernization and do that but
there is a lot of them so of course
there is mention of co lo and there is
even storming worldly Maps tin
topologies there is behavioral code
analysis I mean you don't quote it with
the name but is you mention Cod scene
from Adam torel and more as well so do
we need to use them all or how are we
supposed to choose among them you know
to proceed with our modernization
efforts well I I'll answer the question
maybe JG has some thoughts on this as
well but I'll give you my response first
and then I'll stop talking for a bit I
guess so if you're modernizing you have
to do a lot of things you have to make a
business case what is the business
trying to gain how does the business
plan to grow in the future how is our
current system preventing or making it
too expensive to achieve those business
goals so things like wly mapping to talk
about your strategy you canot do
strategy but you'll probably make a lot
of bad decisions so that you know you
can't really negotiate that then you
have to map out how your system
currently works you have to think about
your current business processes I think
about do we change the business
processes or do we keep them the same
you have to look at your existing code
base and work out how do we refactor it
how do we start to break it apart so the
book does list a lot of techniques like
that but if you're modernizing these are
the things that you have to do strategy
current state future State business
process decoupling your architecture
migrating from the current state to the
Future state so you don't have to use
all the techniques I recommend but you
have to answer all those questions you
can't avoid them really and how can
people choose among those techniques is
there a some simple criteria they can
use if there is one I mean it depends on
what problem you're solving first I
think we always go to the left let's say
with the Y and then we move right to the
house so if someone says to me what do
we do next I have to understand where
are we in the process do we have a
clearly defined business strategy and
problem is solving well we need to start
there first okay if we have that then we
can spend some time thinking about which
are the most important areas of our
business to focus on then we can start
thinking about which parts of the system
would most need to change to improve
those parts of the business then we can
start thinking about how do we start
breaking up the system mapping out the
current state in detail making a future
plan and if we have that plan then we
can start thinking how do we execute how
do we actually put work in our backlog
and start doing the work okay have you
got an example you know again from a
real project in doing this I mean at
least showing how you go from I don't
know from the strategy to the rest of
the work maybe mentioning some of the
tools just to put them in some kind of
place to give people some mental model
on how to think about these things I
think different clients I've worked have
been at different stages for example
worked with a company that electric
vehicle charging infrastructure they
already had a very clear business
strategy they wanted to grow open up
some new I think they were calling them
sites where you can go and actually
charge your car where the electric
vehicle charging stations are installed
for example had a very ambitious
business plan um expanding it across
multiple countries and they were now
wondering okay the business goals are
clear how do we get that on a technical
and an organizational level how do we
start taking the current systems and
having more more clearly defined areas
different business domains and how do we
start organizing our team so that they
can each work independently in different
areas of the company and help us grow as
quickly as possible so the question was
in that case where do we start what's
the right starting point people I worked
with the company The Architects and the
CTO and the CPO they identified some
candidate areas where they thought it
might make sense to start but they had
three of them and they weren't sure
which is the right domain to start with
if we start here it will benefit in this
way but if we start over here we can do
things more customer facing so the
question here was all about how do we
start so in this case me and my
colleague Eduardo we worked in an
enabling role we formed an architecture
modernization enabling team and the goal
of that team was to think about this
modernization journey and to organize
some workshops to decide what would be
the right starting point what would be
the correct domain to start with and
then the next step would be to have this
inperson Workshop where we do event
storming and map out the domain identify
the subdomains in the team structure and
actually build that road map to let's
start modernizing this part of the
business did that answer the question
want me to dig into any those a bit more
detail yeah you know I answer the
question is yeah so you said of course
the strategy was already clear maybe if
the strategy hadn't been clear I would
imagine potentially some workshops
potentially also using some Wordly
mapping to decide which direction
exactly if the strategy wasn't clear we
would have had to go more in that space
there are some caveats around this if
you know that parts of your system need
to be modernized and you want to
demonstrate the foundations and put
those in place well you can start
without a clear strategy yeah so that
those thing could happen in parallel
yeah SE radio has an opening for a
volunteer host to produce five episodes
per year to apply please follow the
instructions on our website at se-
radio.net
contact and now a question I think this
one probably is Jean George because I
see that in your approach you give a
significant role to data engineering at
least reading the book there is an
entire chapter dedicated to it yeah data
engineering data mhes first question
what is the relationship between data
and
architecture so I think you can't do
anything without data so you can do all
the architecture you want all the design
all the modernization you want if you
don't have data you're not going to go
very far in mod systems I see that now
everybody talk about data yeah so well
at least in the system Enterprise
systems that I see that is always very
often at least data engineering team so
probably everybody wants to capitalize
from the knowledge right now when you're
a modernization effort what is the
typical aspects related to data that
maybe a typical project in a typical
system people want to take care of that
maybe were not there you know I can
imagine I don't know when I started
working data was mostly you know
database queries to satisfy user stuff
but now there is more analyzing
interactions trying to get inside so
maybe you can tell us a bit more about
that yeah sure so I think data has
significantly
changed and the data engineering
practice as not and this result
in creating very centralized team and I
completely relate to what Nick was
saying about the two uh the two CTO
fighting a little bit because in big
organization you will very often have a
data organization and you will have some
Enterprise or software organization I
mean Enterprise architecture software
organization and they don't often get
along and this is also due to this
different ways of working okay okay
technically you can call it socio the
socio aspect of the platform the social
aspect of working but it's really about
the ways of working in my experience
I've seen very often centralized data
team that were just
growing I wouldn't say exponentially but
they were growing very fast but just to
cope with what was needed to maintain
and the maintenance cost prevented them
to actually go to some modernization and
so every time I'm not trying to throws a
stone or throw a ball towards you know
the centralized data team but a lot of
what we've seen and for me the book is
also the conclusion probably not the
conclusion but a good step of where
we've been going in modernizing since
the I would say early 2000 to now okay
and you've seen the Advent of agile
methodologies you've seen the Advent of
all this scrum this product thinking Etc
which in software
and of course then in architecture has
been very strong but has not been the
case in data okay data has always
started to focus on I'm going to do my
job okay so when you're thinking about
when I'm discussing with a lot of data
engineering teams or data engineering
organization they say yes we are agile
we're doing sprints okay and basically
their Sprints are mini waterfalls of two
weeks and it's not working so when I say
it's not working it's not scalable okay
so so all the lessons we've learned in
software and that muslin Nick put in the
book we are not using that in the world
of data enough okay so so and I still
think very strongly that data mesh is
one of the solution is probably one of
the idea you want to go towards okay so
if you listen to Gartner or some people
that say oh data mes is already dead or
but if you look also at gner the same
Gardner and they say you look at the
component of what data mesh is and the
four principles that are translated
directly into things that are on the
rise within the gardener environment for
example I think that's that's where we
are okay we want to modernize
architecture for all the good reasons
that Nick said and and you as well
joanni and the thing is right now but
the data needs to follow up okay so is
there's no way we can have a
state-of-the-art architecture or
modernized whichever level of maturity
you want to give it without also
modernizing data have you worked in any
projects in any efforts where actually
data you know modernizing data was the
major driver for an architecture
modernization effort I've seen a few
typically Tuesdays when companies are
going from on Prem to the cloud okay and
large companies not everybody is fully
migrated and some are actually coming
back but the thing is and you see you
see the pitfalls as well when you're
part of this kind of project is that I'm
trying to do a lift and shift okay but
for data having a lift and shift is much
more complicated let's say I'm living on
Prem data warehouse like an exad data or
ter data and I'm going to the cloud and
doing a red shift or big query for
example because usually you also change
the technology of the tools you're using
that is very complicated for as part of
the architecture redesign because the
easy tendency is to say I'm going to
have direct pipelines that are mimicking
what I have on Prem to what I'm going to
do on in the cloud okay and it's very
complicated because first the
Technologies are different second the
expectations are different the billing
is different and the performance is
different so I've seen a lot of project
where things were optimized for on Prem
okay so even using stuff like a SQL
Server completely on the biggest
machines they could have and using SQL
Server as a data warehouse technology on
Prem and then you go to the cloud and
then you say okay I'm going to do red
shift but all the optimization they put
in place for SQL servers the way they
structure because at this point you're
tweaking the architecture you're
tweaking it to you still follow the
guidelines of the architecture but the
implementation is so close to the engine
itself that you're not benefiting from
what for example a red shift could give
you right you're still having the same
models that you would have in SQL Server
if I understand correctly let's see if
I'm understanding correctly your point
basically you're saying when you have an
modernization effort that involves data
so for example Shifting the system
putting that into a cloud from on
premises trying to keep pretty much the
same shape of the system but in the
cloud actually is a problem and probably
a better way to do that would be to
revisit the way data is managed and
maybe you need to do something
differently because if you have stuff
like say on the premises SQL Server
optimized for SQL Server then you move
you said red shift it's like well now we
need to do something different with the
data otherwise will be suboptimal you're
exactly on point and that's why I think
then and I guess that Nick agrees on
that as well is that's why I think like
data product thinking and data contract
as well help us in the data engineering
world to go there because what you're
actually giving your customer is this
agreement this proposal around data
management okay so now I'd like to talk
about the implementation aspects yeah so
the first question is we may be thinking
that we may need to modernize the
architecture yeah maybe we have a gut
field or something that seems to be not
working well you know features that
maybe are a bit slow to be developed or
some aspects like this but what are some
criteria some you know kind of crisp
criteria if you like that we can use to
decide that an architecture is worth
modernizing on the data side it's mainly
for example I would say it's the main
driver is the change of philosophy
versus unram to go into the cloud or new
lows that come in effect okay as you
know I live in the US but I I travel a
lot to Europe and I see the impact of
what GDP has done on data and the
consequential higher maturity when it
comes to governance of data in Europe
versus the US there's also difference
okay so that seems like it's a very
positive difference towards Europe but
there's also a lot of VAR positive
difference towards the us but the thing
is that's probably not the topic for
today I think that what I'm seeing is
that those those are drivers right you
know there's always there's kind of
three main drivers when you're looking
at modernizing a project for me is
either you want to save money you want
to make more money or because the
regulator pushes you to go in a
different way okay so that's I think
that's the main three drivers for me and
very often for data it's a regulation
okay so I work in the financial sector
in the US I work also in healthcare
regulation on data here is is very big
and pushes a lot of of those aspects of
modernization okay you've got to build
more reports you've got to have this
regulatory implementation Etc that's
what the kind of the driver are and in
terms of work the consequence of that is
that you either go the traditional way
and you've got this mini data
engineering project that are going there
or you've got a more Global picture say
okay well now I'm I'm done with that and
I want to do a modern data engineering
approach with once more data contract
data product or data mesh okay so we
understand from the data perspective
what about other aspects so well as we
said data is a lot of regulatory things
it could be even save money or make more
money the other aspects so you know in
addition to data so anything else that
you need modernizing what other criteria
can we use there or are the same or are
the criteria the same I think it can be
various things sometimes it can be
around costs sometimes it can be around
support costs so you might have lots of
very manual support processes you might
have customer support teams or call
centers with hundreds or maybe even a
thousand people and you're like you know
what if our software didn't cause so
many errors or we could fix problems
more automated we could save Millions
over the course of a few years so that
might be one around cost savings I think
most often it's around growth
opportunities like what are the things
that we could do as a company that
currently aren't possible or are too
expensive new products moving into new
markets currently working at payfit a
French company for example being very
successful in payroll now has other big
Ambitions companies grown they want to
build newer products uh grow the company
so they can build more capabilities
become more profitable as a company so
often a lot of these factors are
happening at the same time as the
company's growing the system that was
fine before that worked for one scale
for building one product for a certain
kind of customer suddenly as you want
scale the company and the
organization now the current system is
maybe a bit too coupled in places it
wasn't a problem before but it is now or
as you try and do more things a support
cost grow so yeah it can become
expensive to do things um a sign to look
out for is when maybe you got some
product manager or some salesperson who
says could we build this new API for
this partner it's a really strategic
partner all they need is a search API
that works across three bits of data all
easy that sounds easy that's all they
need and you're like well those three
bits of data live in three different
Legacy systems we have different teams
that own different parts of it those
systems are currently very unreliable we
deploy them once every 3 months and
you're like oh my gosh if I work for any
same company with a good architecture we
can Implement that in a day's worth of
work here it's going to take three or
six months can't we we have to say no to
things that should be very easy and
should be very valuable so that's
something to look out for definitely
when things that are too expensive and
we're saying no to things that could
have a decent impact for the business
actually I've got now the a different
question that is have you ever come
across a situation where you actually
decided you know what it's not worth
modernizing let's keep it this way so
people are considering about modernizing
the system then had a deeper look and
say actually it's not worth the effort
and the cost have you got any example of
this
as a consultant that happens all the
time yeah they call you in they've got
these big ambitious business goals they
want you to tell them how they can
modernize their systems very easily and
you tell them well it's going to take 3
years you're going to have to put some
projects on hold whilst you do the
modernization work you can still do some
Feature work but you have to balance
modernization versus product work and
they're like we can't justify to the CEO
and one client I worked for I was
talking to a chief finance officer and
she was saying why my developers talking
about microservices why do I need to
sign off this budget to do some
modernization work to move to
microservices yeah so this happens for
for a variety of reasons I would even
add to that that I was probably a little
bit more in the Enterprise side as well
is that instead of modernizing it buy
something off the shelf okay and I've
seen this scenario as well so are you
saw are your thinking that you're going
to work on a project which is going to
be build a new feature or feature set
and then at the end of it you're
actually going to to to do an
integration project between your CRM and
your loyalty program for example okay so
there's also this where it's not worth
modernizing the existing or just hey
let's get something off the shelf that's
true sometimes just buying something new
is the is the best idea and I think this
is part of the Strategic work you do at
the beginning of a modernization effort
so maybe with worldly mapping that to
decide what is call to the business what
you can buy and take some decisions in
this respect am I correct yeah
definitely I was in New Zealand a wildo
earlier this year and on day one I did
some events on me with this company and
they mapped out this current system that
needed lots of improvements they were
going to fix every different aspect of
it when we did the wly mapping they were
like we could fix all of these things
and modernize this Legacy system but if
we do that we'll have no time to work on
all of this new AI stuff we want to do
whatever you think about AI you know
let's just put that on hold all this
other new stuff we wanted to do well we
only have a limited amount of people to
work on this and so that pushed them
towards yeah we we could buy something
off the shelf here and that would free
us up to work on these more interesting
AI things that we want to work on okay
and now another question that I suspect
I know the answer but I'm not quite sure
so if you actually come across any
systems that we designed and manag in
such a way to be Evergreen you know
therefore needing no modernization and
often we talk and I talk as well about
you know evolutionary architecture and
this kind of systems that ideally should
allow you to create a system that
follows the business needs and maybe
with a
less amount of technical depth
accumulated so if you come across such a
system in any of P project yeah I've
worked over the last 15 years probably
with two or three companies that fit
that criteria and I'll tell you what was
consistent about those companies they
had teams that were autonomous those
teams were doing extreme programming
practices like tdd andair programming
they were very focused on continuously
improving their work they were talking
about refactoring all the time they were
always trying to learn new stuff they
had like training cars join during work
hours and stuff people might say oh
these are all just Geeks Who are going
crazy about craftsmanship and everything
and and all extreme
programming but those were the companies
I've seen that didn't need to do this
big modernization work because they
built quality into everything they did
and it was an ongoing topic and the fact
that it was ongoing was I guess a
concern also for the senior leadership
to keep this quality high I would
imagine so it was not simply the teams
deciding to do that it was a mix of
having a good CTO who understands the
value of these practices I think the
having a good CTO was consistent in all
those experiences a CTO who understands
quality and having a CEO who trusts the
CTO and people used to say things like
we're not a tech company we're a music
company we're so focused on Tech here
but the CEO could see we had multiple
teams I think at the start there were
six or seven teams and that grew over
the years deploying to production every
day when the business can see results
like that yeah that buys you some space
to you know you don't have to justify
anything when a customer raises a bug
and you fix it in an hour deploy to
production well that kind of buys
yourself some credibility and in a lot
of companies Business Leaders can see
that okay they talk a lot about tech a
lot about refactoring things like DDD
extreme programming but you know they
can see clear results from that yeah
that's quite interesting Nick I have a
question for you you mentioned that
there was three companies over your your
15 years your last 15 years what's the
percentage what the three company
representing the percentage of company
you've dealt with a it's probably about
3%
yeah very small number and even
sometimes it's not even the whole
company it's when you've got a large
company you might have pockets so I
worked with one of the UK's big
Supermarket chains a few years ago they
had some teams who are doing amazing
work and other teams that are building
up a lot of technical debt so yeah in a
big company uh also like when I worked
at Salesforce some teams are doing great
work continuously improving having high
quality and others were just building
bigger and bigger Legacy systems every
day and now a question for I guess both
of you is you know have you got any
recommendations for fitting the
modernization work with other priorities
of the business because I think we men
mentioned this a few times before that
this is one of the contentious points is
like well if we spend time modernizing
we we cannot really spend that time
adding new features but are there any
any suggestions you have to give people
on how to talk about the need of
modernization how to negotiate with
other priorities of course I said both
of you because you know we talk about
that more some of the software aspects
but for data as well and data being
particularly sensitive and complicated
too so I would say a few things that are
always important or very helpful I would
say the first one is having a consistent
message at the C Level so are the CEO
the CTO and the CPO all giving
consistent message or is the CTO talking
about modernization and the chief
product officers talking about lots of
new features well if you're giving mixed
signals at the top of your organization
like that you're already off to a bad
start people in the middle managers the
directors above them the people working
in individual teams like developers and
product managers they will have to
decide modernization or new features
we're we're getting different messages
and most of the time people will just
default to building new features because
that's visible that's what they've
always done and that's what they'll get
rewarded for so you need to have a very
consistent message that modernization
work is important in this company and a
very clear message of what it's worth to
the company of why not building a
feature now is worth 10 or 100 times x
more value in one or two years time so a
clear connection between modernization
of business goals consistent message and
a consistent message from the different
leaders at different levels of the
company as well so there's no doubt I
would say those are the fundamentals and
then when you're building your road maps
for the year or for the quarter or for
the semester again that's another chance
where have to make more fine grain
decisions I think building different
possibilities is key so build three
different road maps I would say what's
your lots of modernization not much
product work what's an equal balance and
then what's mostly product and not
modernization so you can talk about the
different tradeoffs and you can ask
different stakeholders to give inputs on
which one they value the most I would
say in data all that applies but one
thing which is pretty
difficult in the data world is to
measure the r of data okay so what's my
return on investment when it comes to
data project one of my recent experience
was in the risk division of a major
fintech and how do you
measure that you didn't get fine you
didn't get any money stolen or you know
it's very it's very difficult okay to to
to determine that but you've got to find
this kpis
and you've got to stick to them and as
Nick was saying you've got to report
that to your CPO CTO and CEO okay you've
got to report to your leadership all you
doing this kpis and before you start the
project you've got to do that and I
think that if you keep that in mind as
Nick was saying for the Green Field his
lucky three Greenfield project you can
get almost anything okay so so then you
get the credibility you're constantly on
your kpis you're constantly delivering
value to to the organization and then
it's easier to say okay well now I want
to start this project okay but it's
always going back to it starts with a
business
decision okay and now let's try to end
with a bank so a good question to end
with a negative note how often do
architecture modernization programs
succeed or fail in your experience I've
been burned a lot of times by things
that didn't work out you know like I've
been involved in projects where say
things like yeah we promise we'll let
you focus on that this year and then
before you've even really got started
it's like can we build this one new
thing this big new product feature it
might take a couple of months but once
this is done then we'll get to this
deeper modernization work and then it
just carries on and you actually don't
do any modernization work how often does
this happen is it a common thing is it
something you found in many places this
kind of attitude in your yeah it's quite
frequent I would say ones that work the
best are ones like the UK government
where you have this minimum level when
you have a very strong problem or crisis
like the government had that's always a
very strong motivator that helps you to
modernize because there's a clear need
it's hard to avoid it and when you have
those standards those minimum acceptable
levels those global policies that means
you you have a need and you have some
standards So you you're going to
modernize and you're going to do it to a
good standard not taking shortcuts
because that's not allowed so when those
recipes are there yeah normally does
work out maybe not everything goes
perfectly of course but less than half
the time maybe 25% of the time I would
say things go really well over the
course of two or three years and so if
you would some up you know let's say the
most three or four common causes of
failure what would they be in your
experience yeah the first one is like I
said before not having a strong enough
reason and a compelling reason and
sticking to that reason and not just
defaulting back to product work that
would be the first one then I think it's
around having the expertise in the
company to do modernization work
sometimes yeah the top of the company
the CTO might have a big Vision but you
look at how the teams are working they
don't understand why it's important to
decouple different parts of the system
they don't understand Concepts like DDD
they don't understand why it's important
to decouple your business logic your
application layer logic and your UI like
we've always just built these things
tightly inter mingled what would be the
benefit of doing that so I think the
other ones having the skills to do that
yeah so the the vision the skills and
then the third one is probably things
normally get stuck you can get stuck in
a halfway phase where you start
modernizing and don't finish and you got
the bits of a new system and bits of an
old system so I think really thinking
who the migration plan of how you get
from A to B doesn't need to be fully
defined up front but you need to really
think ahead to what can stop us
finishing the
migration and what can we do to predict
and anticipate as many of those things
as possible so that we don't end up in a
state where we're stuck halfway and the
system's more complex than it was before
and I would say one of the examples that
I see a lot there is when companies have
some kind of platform or some patterns
where the new system can talk to the old
system maybe you have an event driven
architecture and you can easily publish
an event from the Legacy which is
consumed by the new system or the new
system can publish in events and it can
be handled by the Legacy so having those
things able to talk to each other easily
reduces a lot of the friction there I
would say but it's not the only thing
but one of the things to think about so
it seems to me that the last point maybe
is kind of lack of appropriate planning
really it's like when you say you know
when you talk about not being stopped
halfway finding big risks that were not
anticipated so seems that people don't
take their time to actually plan it's
partially planning but it's also around
discipline you know once we start this
thing if someone tempts us to build a
new product feature we have to be really
disciplined and say we're halfway
through this migration from the old to
the new we currently have a lot of
complexity it might be even more complex
than before we started CU we have new
and old data in different places this UI
shows one price this UI over here shows
a different price we want to avoid this
synchronization issues which can happen
with mid migration so it can be planning
but it can also be as I was saying
discipline to not diverge from the plan
or to not make too many concessions okay
and how can we increase the chances of
success then you know going back over
your series of questions here I've been
lucky I would say enough that I've been
in projects where modernization was
always a
success but it was not always the
expected goal we said at the beginning
okay but as Nick was saying you've got
to be very careful and not to having
like two systems that runs in parallel
but my experience maybe I was lucky
enough is that we always managed to
bring incremental value even through
modernization
okay so and that's I think something to
keep in mind because yes you can have
this big planning and I agree that for
some project you don't have a choice
having this major planning but if you're
good at agile you don't always have this
you've got a road map but you don't have
a second by second planning right so I
think that here you can still combine
that with incremental added value to
your modernization like for any project
yeah
yeah Nick anything to add to this I
agree I think it's it's always going to
be an ongoing Balancing Act you just
need to make sure that it doesn't
balance too much in the way of new
product features and you don't do any
modernization work and you're stuck in
this halfway State I work with people a
lot and we often talk about
modernization and they're going to get
something out of this but they don't
want to do it it might be an engineer or
a customer support person and they're
like yeah cuz the last one didn't f
finish now I have to use three systems
and not two systems so not finishing can
have big consequences so you know the
key thing is to make sure we do keep
making progress either we don't do it or
we finish it but we don't want the worst
thing which is to be stuck halfway and
have this Frankenstein system I've
worked in several of those systems to
help fixing them I've experience with
especially big banks at this thing like
that one system they they said that they
needed to mod and create a completely
new one and then they had two systems to
manage and then they said the second one
was not good enough and create the third
one and then they have three systems in
produ exactly to be kept inly that
exactly okay guys so now I think we'll
it's time to wrap up I think we've done
a quite a good job introducing
architecture modernization so thank you
very much was there anything we missed
that you'd like to mention don't forget
the data
we won't thank you Nick and Jean George
for coming to the show has been a great
pleasure for me and this is joavan as
proni for software engineering radio
thank you for listening thank you thank
you
Javan thanks for listening to SC radio
an educational program brought to you by
It software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at sc-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]